Register of the John F. Russell collection
Hoover Institution Archives
John F. Russell collection
1930-1976
85015
Hoover Institution Archives
63 manuscript boxes (26.3 linear feet)
Reports, studies, letters, memoranda, dossiers, notes, bulletins, pamphlets, serial issues, clippings, printed ephemera, and audiovisual material relating to communism and subversion in the United States, primarily in the post-World War II period. Includes material generated by the United States Army Counter Intelligence Corps.
Russell, John F., collector.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The Hoover Institution Archives acquired the John F. Russell collection from Russell in 1985. Little is known of its origin apart from what may be inferred from internal evidence. In the early 1950s, John F. Russell was a lieutenant in the United States Army Counter Intelligence Corps, stationed at Fort Holabird, Maryland, and associated with the Army's Counter Intelligence School there. No information on his later career is available. Much of the material in the collection dates from the 1950s, and a portion of this was clearly generated by the Counter Intelligence Corps, some of it perhaps by Russell. Later typescript and mimeographed material derives from various and unattributed sources.
In addition to Russell, others involved in bringing the material together included Bernard J. Sweeney, W. Fairfield Peterson, George Pfister and Nick D'Angelo. Sweeney was a major in the Counter Intelligence Corps, also stationed at Fort Holabird and perhaps Russell's commanding officer. Peterson, some of whose correspondence appears in the collection, was a civilian anti-communist activist living in Baltimore. There is no information on Pfister or D'Angelo. Much of the collected printed and near-print material solicited from left-wing sources for the collection was mailed to D'Angelo at a post office box in Baltimore. It is possible that the name was a pseudonym.
A small quantity of older material includes original 1930 documents of the American Vigilant Intelligence Federation. There is no indication of how or why Russell came into possession of it.
Printed and near-print material from the 1960s and 1970s includes official publications of the Department of Defense and the United States Information Agency. There is no explanation for Russell's acquisition of them.
Scope and Content of Collection
The focus of the collection is on issues of communism and subversion within the United States. The General Subject File consists of material arranged by organization or topical area suspected of being under communist influence and the Individual Subject File by name of suspect individual. These files show interest in communist influence in liberal organizations, labor, civil rights movements, education, bookstores and publishers, the press, radio and television, Hollywood, religion (including the Catholic Church, assorted Protestant denominations, Jewry, esoteric societies such as Rosicrucians and Illuminati, and the Moral Re-Armament movement), among proponents of the United Nations and world government, within the United States government (especially the Department of State), and as related to immigration and peace issues.
The collection is of special significance because of its documentation of active United States Army concern with communist issues affecting the domestic civilian population of the United States. Material within the General Subject File on communist influence within the United States Armed Forces is also of particular interest in light of the related charges by Senator Joseph R. McCarthy that ultimately resulted in his downfall. A series of United States Department of Defense Issuances includes instructional materials on communism generated by the Army's Counter Intelligence Corps at the Fort Holabird Counter Intelligence School. A series of United States Information Agency Issuances is primarily concerned with international aspects of communism. Other series of printed matter, including United States Congressional Issuances, United States Federal Bureau of Investigation Issuances, United States Subversive Activities Control Board Issuances, United States Court Documents, University Course Bulletins, and Serial Issues and Pamphlets emanating from various sources, are all centrally concerned with communism and subversion issues. There is also a small Audiovisual File.
Communism--United States.; Socialism--United States.; Subversive activities--United States.
- General Subject File, 1930-1973 (Boxes 1-26)
  Scope and Contents note
  Reports, studies, memoranda, notes, letters, circulated documents, brochures, leaflets, flyers, bulletins, newsletters, clippings, and typed copies of printed matter relating primarily to communist influence within various areas of American life. Includes a few pamphlets and serial issues.
  - Africa (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Amerasia (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - American Association of University Professors (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - American Civil Liberties Union (Box-folder 1: 5-7)
    Includes photocopy of lengthy typescript study.
  - American Committee for Cultural Freedom (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - American Committee in Aid of Chinese Industrial Cooperatives (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - American Committee on Africa (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - American Communications Association (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - American Federation of Labor (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - American Friends Service Committee (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - American Humane Association (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - American Labor Party (Box-folder 2: 7-9)
  - American League against War and Fascism (Box-folder 2: 10)
    Includes material on American League for Peace and Democracy.
  - American Library Association (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - American National Theater Academy (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - American Nazi Party (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - American Peace Crusade (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - American Peace Mobilization (Box-folder 3: 2)
    Includes material on American People's Mobilization.
  - American Peoples' Congress and Exposition for Peace (1951: Chicago) (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - American Russian Institute (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - American Socialist Union (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - American Soviet Council (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - American Veterans Committee (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - American Veterans for Peace (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - American Youth Congress (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - American Youth for Democracy (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - American Zionist Council (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Americans for Democratic Action (Box-folder 3: 12-14)
    Includes lengthy mimeographed study prepared by the staff of the United States Senate Republican Policy Committee.
  - Anti-Conscription Committee (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith (Box-folder 4: 2)
    Includes copies of correspondence with General George E. Stratemeyer.
  - Argentina (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Armed Forces (Box-folder 4: 4)
    Includes memoranda on communist influence within U.S. Armed Forces; typescript studies of 1954 Fort Monmouth investigation and subsequent censure of Senator Joseph R. McCarthy; copies of World War II-era U.S. Army orientation fact sheets; and issues of Vietnam War-era GI newspaper The Bond.
  - Arms of Friendship, Inc. (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Art Book Guild of America (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Asia (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Atheism (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Baltimore County Committee for Peace (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Baltimore Forum (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Baltimore Youth for Peace (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Baptist churches (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Bill of Rights Conference (1949: New York City) (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Books and bookstores (general) (Box-folder 4: 14-15)
  - Budget Book Bar (New York City) (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Campaign for World Government (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Camps (resorts) (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Canada (Box-folder 5: 5)
    Includes lengthy typescript on communism in Canada.
  - Catholic Church (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Catholic Worker Movement (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - China (Box-folder 5: 9)
    Includes typescript statement by Reverend Raymond J. de Jaegher (missionary in China) and a typed translation of a Taiwanese intelligence report.
  - China Welfare Appeal (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Citizens Committee for Constitutional Liberties (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Citizens Emergency Defense Conference (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Civil liberties (general) (Box-folder 5: 13)
    Includes mimeographed American Legion report on Congressional witnesses invoking Fifth Amendment.
  - Civil Liberties Legal Defense Fund (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Civil Rights Congress (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
  - Comic books (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Committee for a Democratic Far Eastern Policy (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Committee for Free Political Advocacy (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Committee for Nonviolent Action (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Committee for Peaceful Alternatives (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Commonwealth College (Mena, Arkansas) (Box-folder 6: 8)
    Includes photocopy of lengthy Arkansas General Assembly Joint Committee report.
  - Commonwealth College (Mena, Arkansas) (cont'd.) (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Communism (general)
    - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - Studies (typescript and mimeographed)
      - Attributed to John F. Russell. "Organization of the Communist Party, USA" and "Why Do People Join the Communist Movement?" (Box-folder 7: 3)
      - Authorship unattributed
        - "The Communist Underground" and "Communist Underground Operations" (Box-folder 7: 4)
        - "Rise and Continuity of Dictatorship in Russia" (Box-folder 7: 5)
        - Untitled studies of history and splits (Box-folder 7: 6)
        - Untitled study of propaganda (Box-folder 7: 7)
        - Untitled study of symbolism (Box-folder 7: 8)
        - Miscellaneous studies (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
        - Notes and fragments (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - All-American Conference to Combat Communism prospectus (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - American Bar Association reports (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - American Legion issuances (Box-folder 8: 6)
      Includes proceedings of 1949 Counter-Subversive Activities Conferences.
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation records, 1930 (Box-folder 8: 7)
      Reports and correspondence of the Federation with Congressman Hamilton Fish and others.
    - Communist International issuances (Box-folder 8: 8)
      Mainly typed copies of resolutions and decisions of Comintern congresses.
    - Communist International issuances (cont'd.) (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
    - Communist Party, U.S.A. issuances (Box-folder 9: 3-5)
      Includes typed copies of constitution and organizational manual.
    - Marx, Karl, and Friedrich Engels (Box-folder 9: 6)
      Mimeographed copies of writings.
    - Mosinee pageant, 1950 (Box-folder 9: 7)
      Mock newspaper issue announcing communist takeover of Mosinee, Wisconsin, as part of anti-communist pageant.
    - Miscellaneous printed and mimeographed matter (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
      Includes text of 1951 indictment of Communist Party, U.S.A. leaders and the 1953 Democratic National Committee statement of Democratic Party record against communism.
    - Bibliographies (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Communist front organizations (general) (Box-folder 10: 4)
    Includes typescript studies.
  - Communists (general) (Box-folder 10: 5)
    Includes memoranda re multiple individuals and compilation of newspaper photographs of multiple individuals.
  - Compass (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Confluence (Box-folder 10: 7)
    Includes letter by Henry A. Kissinger.
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Congress of Racial Equality (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - Consumers Union (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - Crime (Box-folder 10: 11)
  - Cross World Books (Chicago) (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - Crosscurrents Press (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - Cuba (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - Culture (general) (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Czechoslovakia (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - Dialectical materialism (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - Dissent (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Distributive, Processing and Office Workers of America (Box-folder 11: 8)
    Includes lengthy mimeographed study.
  - Drugs (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - Economics (Box-folder 11: 10)
  - Education (Box-folder 11: 11-13)
    Mainly re communist influence in education. Includes National Council for American Education reports on communism at Harvard University and Yale University.
  - Emergency Civil Liberties Committee (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Encampment for Citizenship (1953: New York City) (Box-folder 12: 2)
    Political Action Workshop meeting materials.
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica Films (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - Episcopal Church (Box-folder 12: 4)
    Includes correspondence between Noble C. Powell, Episcopal Bishop of Maryland, and W. Fairfield Peterson.
  - Espionage (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - Europe (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - Faculty of Social Science (New York City) (Box-folder 12: 7)
  - Fair Play for Cuba Committee (Box-folder 12: 8)
  - Farmers (Box-folder 12: 9)
    Includes Eastern Union Farmer issues and Facts for Farmers issues (Farm Research, Inc.).
  - Fascism (Box-folder 12: 10)
    Includes 1942 Library of Congress bibliography on "Nazi Fifth Column Activities."
  - Federal Writers' Project (Box-folder 12: 11)
  - Federation of American Scientists (Box-folder 12: 12)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation (Box-folder 12: 13)
  - Finance (Box-folder 12: 14)
  - Ford Foundation (Box-folder 12: 15)
  - Foreign agents (Box-folder 12: 16)
    Includes U.S. Attorney General's reports for 1953 and 1955 on registered foreign agents.
  - Foreign Policy Association (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - Foundation Farthest Out, Inc. (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - Foundations (Box-folder 13: 3)
    Mainly re communist influence in foundations. Includes 1954 press releases of U.S. House of Representatives Special Committee to Investigate Tax Exempt Foundations.
  - Four Continent Book Corporation (New York City) (Box-folder 13: 4-5)
  - Freemasons (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - Freethinkers of America (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - Freethought Press Association (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Freethought Society of America (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - Fund for the Republic (Box-folder 13: 10-11)
    Includes mimeographed report and radio broadcast transcripts by Fulton Lewis, Jr.
  - Germany (Box-folder 14: 1)
    Includes 1945 typescript statement by Ralph U. C. Penning.
  - Government (Box-folder 14: 2)
    Includes typescript and mimeographed studies of communist influence within the U.S. government.
  - Greece (Box-folder 14: 3)
  - Hawaii (Box-folder 14: 4)
    Mainly re communist influence in Hawaii.
  - Health (Box-folder 14: 5)
  - Henry George School of Social Science (New York City) (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - Highlander Folk School (Monteagle, Tennessee) (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - Homosexuality (Box-folder 14: 8)
    Typed copies of letters by unidentified homosexual member of the U.S. Armed Forces.
  - Humanism (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - Humanity Guild (Box-folder 14: 10)
  - Illuminati (Box-folder 14: 11)
    Includes issues of News Behind the News, mimeographed newsletter published in Ontario by the National Federation Christian Laymen and concerned with exposure of Illuminati influence.
  - Immigration (Box-folder 14: 12-14)
    Includes lengthy mimeographed study of the McCarran-Walter Immigration Act and a lengthy mimeographed U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service documentary brief on the Communist Party, U.S.A.
  - Immigration (cont'd.) (Box-folder 15: 1)
  - Imported Publications and Products (New York City) (Box-folder 15: 2)
  - Independent Citizens Committee of the Arts, Sciences and Professions (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - Institute for Democratic Education (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - Institute for International Order (Box-folder 15: 5)
  - Institute for the Study of the USSR (Box-folder 15: 6)
  - Institute of General Semantics (Box-folder 15: 7)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations (Box-folder 15: 8)
  - International Arts and Sciences Press (Box-folder 15: 9)
  - International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (Box-folder 15: 10)
  - International Publishers (Box-folder 15: 11)
  - International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers (Box-folder 15: 12)
  - International Union of Students (Box-folder 15: 13)
  - International Workers Order (Box-folder 15: 14)
  - Israel (Box-folder 15: 15)
  - Japan (Box-folder 15: 16)
    Includes 1949 Japan Federation of Employers' Association report on labor relations.
  - Jefferson School of Social Science (New York City) (Box-folder 15: 17)
  - Jews and antisemitism (Box-folder 16: 1)
    Includes Christian National Crusade (Gerald L. K. Smith) issuances and issues of The Point, a Catholic antisemitic publication.
  - Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee (Box-folder 16: 2)
    Appellant brief in 1949 case of Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee vs. Clark et al.
  - Korea and Korean War (Box-folder 16: 3-4)
    Includes photocopies of Korean-language documents.
  - Labor (general) (Box-folder 16: 5-6)
    Includes several typescript studies.
  - Labor Youth League (Box-folder 16: 7)
  - Labor's Non-Partisan League (Box-folder 16: 8)
  - Latin America (Box-folder 17: 1)
    Mainly re communism in Latin America. Includes mimeographed Pan American Union study.
  - Law (Box-folder 17: 2-3)
    Mainly re litigation involving communist issues. Includes legal briefs in such cases.
  - League for Industrial Democracy (Box-folder 17: 4)
  - League of Women Voters (Box-folder 17: 5)
  - Libertarian League (Box-folder 17: 6)
  - Libertarian Socialist Committee (Box-folder 17: 7)
  - Loyalty-security program (Box-folder 17: 8-9)
    Includes U.S. Civil Service Commission manuals for conducting loyalty-security investigations; U.S. government instructions, procedures, and reports re loyalty-security investigations; and an Ernest O. Lawrence Radiation Laboratory security manual.
  - Loyalty-security program (cont'd.) (Box-folder 18: 1-3)
  - Maryland Committee for Democratic Rights (Box-folder 18: 4)
  - Maryland Committee for Peace (Box-folder 18: 5)
  - Maryland Committee to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee (Box-folder 18: 6)
  - Maryland Peace Council (Box-folder 18: 7)
  - Maryland Socialist League (Box-folder 18: 8)
  - Marzani and Munsell (Publishers) (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - Masses and Mainstream (Box-folder 19: 2)
  - May Day (Box-folder 19: 3)
  - Meals for Millions, Inc. (Box-folder 19: 4)
  - Methodist churches (Box-folder 19: 5)
    Includes material on the Methodist Federation for Social Action.
  - Middle East (Box-folder 19: 6)
  - Middle East Institute (Box-folder 19: 7)
  - Monthly Review (Box-folder 19: 8)
  - Moral Re-Armament Movement (Box-folder 19: 9)
    Includes material on Frank Buchman.
  - Motion pictures (Box-folder 19: 10)
    Mainly re communist influence in Hollywood.
  - Music (Box-folder 19: 11)
    Includes material on recording companies.
  - Nation (Box-folder 19: 12)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (Box-folder 19: 13)
    Includes pamphlets on communist influence in the Association published by the Georgia Commission on Education.
  - National Child Labor Committee (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - National Civic-Minded League (Box-folder 20: 2)
  - National Committee for an Effective Congress (Box-folder 20: 3)
  - National Committee for Peaceful Alternatives (Box-folder 20: 4)
  - National Committee for the Defense of Political Prisoners (Box-folder 20: 5)
    Includes material on the National Committee for People's Rights.
  - National Committee to Defend Negro Leadership (Box-folder 20: 6)
  - National Committee to Repeal the McCarran Act (Box-folder 20: 7)
  - National Conference for New Politics (Box-folder 20: 8)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews (Box-folder 20: 9)
  - National Council against Conscription (Box-folder 20: 10)
  - National Council for Prevention of War (Box-folder 20: 11)
  - National Council of American-Soviet Friendship (Box-folder 20: 12)
  - National Council of the Churches of Christ (Box-folder 20: 13)
    Includes material on predecessor Federal Council of Churches.
  - National Education Association (Box-folder 20: 14)
  - National Federation for Constitutional Liberties (Box-folder 20: 15)
  - National Guardian (Box-folder 20: 16)
  - National Issues Committee (Box-folder 20: 17)
  - National Lawyers Guild (Box-folder 20: 18)
  - National Negro Congress (Box-folder 20: 19)
  - National Negro Labor Council (Box-folder 20: 20)
  - National Non-Partisan Committee to Defend the Rights of the 12 Communist Leaders (Box-folder 20: 21)
  - National Religion and Labor Foundation (Box-folder 20: 22)
  - National Tax Reform Committee (Box-folder 20: 23)
  - National Union of Marine Cooks and Stewards (Box-folder 20: 24)
  - National Veterans Organization (Box-folder 20: 25)
  - National Youth Assembly against Universal Military Training (1948: Washington, D.C.) (Box-folder 20: 26)
  - Nationwide Wholesalers Service (Box-folder 20: 27)
  - New Century Publishers (Box-folder 20: 28)
  - New Horizons for Youth (Box-folder 20: 29)
  - New Leader (Box-folder 20: 30)
  - New Left School of Los Angeles (Box-folder 20: 31)
  - New Party (Box-folder 20: 32)
  - New Republic (Box-folder 20: 33)
  - New Times (Box-folder 20: 34)
  - New World Review (Box-folder 20: 35)
  - New York Times (Box-folder 20: 36)
    Includes analyses of communist influence in the newspaper.
  - Nonviolent Committee for Cuban Independence (Box-folder 21: 1)
  - Open Forum of Maryland (Box-folder 21: 2)
  - Pan-Pacific Women's Association (Box-folder 21: 3)
  - Pasadena Citizens Action Committee (Box-folder 21: 4)
  - Peace (general) (Box-folder 21: 5)
  - Peacemakers (organization) (Box-folder 21: 6)
  - Physicians Forum (Box-folder 21: 7)
  - Politics (general) (Box-folder 21: 8)
    Includes typescript statement by Donald A. Surine re Maryland election campaign irregularities.
  - Polycultural Institution of America (Box-folder 21: 9)
  - Poznan Fund (Box-folder 21: 10)
  - Press (general) (Box-folder 21: 11)
    Mainly re communist influence in the mainstream press.
  - Progress Books (Toronto) (Box-folder 21: 12-13)
  - Progressive (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - Progressive Party (Box-folder 22: 2)
    Includes material on Progressive Citizens of America and on the Independent Progressive Party.
  - Protestant (magazine) (Box-folder 22: 3)
  - Provisional Organizing Committee for a Marxist-Leninist Communist Party (Box-folder 22: 4)
  - Psychiatry (Box-folder 22: 5)
  - Puerto Rico (Box-folder 22: 6)
  - Quakers (Box-folder 22: 7)
  - Race (general) (Box-folder 22: 8)
    Includes Citizens' Councils pamphlets and New York state investigative reports re 1949 Peekskill, New York, riot.
  - Radio and television (Box-folder 22: 9)
    Mainly re communist influence in the industry.
  - Ramparts (Box-folder 22: 10)